Good morning today's דף daf is ל"ח Lamed Chet and we pick
up at the very very top of ל"ז עמוד ב' Lamed Zayin
Amud Bet at the שתי תפוחה shtei tapucha and let's take a
look. כמה היא קשוייה רבי מאיר אומר. Kama hi kishuya Rabbi Meir
omer. So now we've discussed what are the circumstances in which the
child pains, the קשוי kishuy makes the blood not דם זיבה dam
ziva and now we're asking how long of a period going back
is this going to be relevant for? Can we still attribute it
to childbirth? So Rabbi Meir says forty or fifty days and another
opinion is a month and another opinion is two weeks. So let's
take a look. So
the
גמרא Gemara says השתא חמשים מקשיה ארבעים מיבעיא? Hashata chamishim makshia arba'im
mibaya? If she fifty days it's considered to be child pains and
it can be attributed to the birth, is there any question about
forty days? Now that's a little bit funny because normally you'd say
if he says forty or fifty days it means however far back
maybe the entire nine months and there are times where we say
forty or fifty days like the first משנה mishna in סוכה Suka
says that you know how big can a סוכה suka be and
Rabbi Yehuda says forty or fifty אמות amot and nobody thinks it
means literal it means it can be however tall you want it.
So תוספות Tosfot points that out but we're going to see later
in a few on ל"ח Lamed Chet in a few lines that
Rabbi Meir treats fifty as precise that he actually gives a count
of exactly how many days it could be and he considers fifty
to be precise. So the גמרא Gemara here wants to know if
fifty is the precise amount why are you saying forty? So אמר
רב חסדא לא קשיא Amar Rav Chisda lo kashya it's not difficult.
כאן חולה כאן בריאה. Kan chola kan bria. It matters if she's
sick or if she's healthy. Doesn't exactly say which way it goes
but רש"י Rashi says if she's sick then you could imagine that
the bleeding is more attributable to the child she has a weaker
constitution so maybe it can cause bleeding at an earlier stage whereas
if she's healthy only forty days back but if she's sick even
up to or weak even up to fifty days back we attribute
it to the infant if it comes with pains. אמר רבי לוי
אין הדם מטהר אלא ימים הראוים להיות בהן זבה. Amar Rabbi Levi
ein hadam metaher ela yamim harauyim lihyot bahen zava.
Now remember the key here is that these pains when they come
at the same time of bleeding can say that the blood is
not a problem if it is blood during the זיבה ziva period.
Blood during the נידה nida period is a problem. So Rabbi Levi
says this works only during the period that she is fit to
be a
זבה. zava. ורבא אמר אפילו בימים הראוים לספירת זבה. V'Rava amar afilu
biyamim harauyim lisphirat zava. What is this ספירה? sphira? It means a
woman anyway cannot be a זבה zava unless she's already bled once
and she's been a נידה. nida. So let's imagine that a woman
bled I don't know during she's now been pregnant for a few
months and now she is in month six or something and she
bleeds once. That makes her a נידה nida because you know unless
you've bled right before the last time you bled you're a נידה
nida not a זבה. zava. Now starting on day eight she can
if she were to bleed starting on day eight from the day
she bled. It's now January one. It's her sixth month of pregnancy.
January one she bleeds. She's a נידה. nida. January eight if she
were to bleed she would be a זבה zava or the after
the seven days of נידה nida bleeding.
So now any blood she has from January eight to eighteen is
potentially זבה zava blood and that still don't have a we still
don't have a what do you call it a marker. But here
let me try to use the back again these things for three-dimensional
it's excitement so much though. Okay so here's January one she bleeds
it's her sixth month of pregnancy. Any so she's a נידה nida
because you can only be a זבה zava if you're bleeding right
after having become having been bled before. So these seven days if
she were to bleed she'd be a נידה nida if she has
it with pains it doesn't matter the pains don't help for נידה
nida bleeding she's a נידה. nida. Now you start January eight okay
any blood she has from January eight to January eighteen is going
to be with comes with the pains that will be זיבה ziva
bleeding right because it comes after from day eight to eighteen after
the נידה nida bleeding and so coming with the pains she is
going to be טהורה tehora because if it comes with the pains
and it's right before childbirth. Now let's say however that she did
not bleed here let's say however she bleeds you know even going
like further out or better scenario let's say she bleeds here and
it's with the childbirth pains and then she bleeds again here with
the childbirth pains and then she bleeds again here and then she
bleeds again here and so on until how far are you going
to call that potential זבה zava blood that is being made טהור
tahor because of the pains? At what stage are you going to
say no no no already that should be נידה nida blood and
it's going to be טמא? tamei? Okay so this is the question
it only makes טהור tahor the זבה zava blood how far of
a period you consider that to be? So let's take a look
at that in the
גמרא Gemara just one minute.
Okay so רב חסדא Rav Chisda says for I'm sorry so אמר
רבי לוי אין הדם מטהר אלא ימים הראוים להיות בהן זבה. Amar
Rabbi Levi ein hadam metaher ela yamim harauyim lihyot bahen zava. It's
only these eleven days from January eight to eighteen assuming she bled
on January one. assuming her pregnancy that any bleeding will be okay.
After this it deserves to be נדה niddah bleeding if after the
eighteen days and bleeding will be טמא tameh even with the pains.
That's what he says.
So ורבא אמר אפילו בימים הראויים לספירת זיבה. v'Rava amar afilu b'yamim
hareuyim l'sfirat zivah. רבא Rava says no. רבא Rava says look. If
she were to have been a זבה zavah during this period of
time, she would need seven clean days afterwards, right? And so it's
possible, which are the days that are relevant to the זבה? zavah?
Not just this period here, but this period plus seven days. Because
it's possible had she become a זבה zavah on the last three
days here, sixteenth, seventeenth, eighteenth, and then she would need seven more
days to become טהור. tahor. So any bleeding not only through day
eighteen, but through day eighteen plus seven, through twenty-five, all of those
is considered related to a potential זבה zavah and any bleeding during
that period with the pains she is טהור. tahor. That's what רבא
Rava says.
Even though she didn't bleed here. And even though she bled here
she's not a זבה. zavah. But once she had one bleeding that
made her a נדה, niddah, all of this is considered relevant. Because
had she bled here and bled again here,
even on the following seven days it would be kind of attached
to the previous זבה.
zavah. Now you could have said maybe if she bleeds three times
with pains she gets extra days here, but he's not, presumably not
saying that. Okay. So let's take a look.
So it says like this. ואמר רב אדא בר אהבה. V'amar Rav
Adda bar Ahava. רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava goes
even further. If you thought רבא Rava was a stretch. ולטעמיה דרבא,
U'l'taimei d'Rava, according to the reasoning of רבא, Rava, אפילו ימים הראויים
לספירת סתירת זיבה. afilu yamim hareuyim l'sfirat stirat zivah.
So he basically says it goes on ad infinitum. That once she
bleeds once here and becomes a נדה, niddah, then you begin a
period where she could be a זבה. zavah. Once you begin a
period that she could be a זבה, zavah, the entire rest of
the time could potentially be זבה zavah time. Why? Because if she
bled three times during the זבה zavah period, then if any time
she would have bled after that could have interrupted a seven clean
day count, right? So she became a זבה zavah here, then it
could be she doesn't stop being a זבה zavah after seven days
because maybe there would have been blood in the first seven days.
And it doesn't mean she stops being a זבה zavah after fourteen
days because maybe there would have been blood in the next seven
days. So any time afterwards could potentially be an extension of having
been a זבה zavah here if she could never get seven clean
days. So this is actually a big קולא. kula. He actually says
that the קושי koshi is מטהר metaher and what that really means
is any blood that comes after having been a נדה niddah is
considered זבה zavah blood and is טהור. tahor. So it's a real
expansion of this case. Because until now we've only been saying it
works for זבה zavah blood. But he really says anything after the
first bleeding, starting on day eight after the first bleeding is potentially
זבה zavah blood. That's what he says. תנן. Tnan. Now let's see
which works out. Okay. Second line, דף ע"ח. daf ayin chet. כמה
הוא קישוייה? Kama hu kishueha?
How far back can it go? רבי מאיר אומר ארבעים וחמישים יום.
Rabbi Meir omer arba'im v'chamishim yom. Up to forty or fifty days
before pregnancy the קושי koshi can help. בשלמא לרבא מסתייעא כרב אדא
בר אהבה. Bishlama l'Rava mista-ei-ach k'Rav Adda bar Ahava.
So according to רבא, Rava, the way he's interpreted like רב אדא
בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava that basically any time is זבה
zavah time after the first seven days, so you'll understand how you
could have a stretch of forty or fifty days that could all
be relevant to the קישוי. kishuy. Because after there was a bleeding
you could have the next forty, fifty, or a hundred days that
are according to this considered to be זבה zavah related days and
טהור. tahor. So the saying fifty days works fine. אלא לוי קשיא.
Ela Levi kashya. According to לוי Levi it's difficult. You'll never get
a stretch of fifty days that it'll always be okay. Right? There'll
be eleven days that'll be okay but the next period the bleeding
will be problematic. Right? Is that clear? Meaning if you're going back
forty or fifty days, she's going to give birth here, what would
it be? January, February, March... let's say she's going to give birth
mid-February. And you go back to the beginning of January. You're not
going to get all the days of January and half the days
of February that could become טהור. tahor. According to him you're only
going to get the first eleven days after the bleeding that could
be solved, not the entire stretch of forty or fifty days. So
how could we say all of those days could be okay?
So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר לך לוי מי קתני טהורה בכולן?
Amar lach Levi: Mi tani tahora b'kullan? No,
it doesn't say for the stretch of forty or fifty days she'll
always be טהורה tahora if she sees blood. What it's saying, what
it means is: בימי נדה נדה בימי זיבה טהורה. Bi-y'mei niddah niddah,
bi-y'mei zivah tahorah. It means during this period of forty or fifty
days prior the laws of קישוי kishuy applied. Now what are the
laws of קישוי? kishuy? The laws of קישוי kishuy are, if they
come during the נדה niddah period it doesn't help, she's a נדה,
niddah, if it comes during the זבה zavah period she's טהורה. tahora.
So it's not saying that for the entire stretch she's טהורה. tahora.
It's just saying that it will be relevant during those forty or
fifty days when it comes during the זבה zavah period. Okay. Is
that clear? Yeah. Can I ask you one thing?
Why לוי Levi doesn't accept the idea you expressed first about these
could always become זבה zavah days?
Because in reality they are not yet זבה zavah days. If she
hadn't bled here, even if she had, she wouldn't be a זבה
zavah because of the law of the child pains, of קישוי. kishuy.
Correct. So the reality is... She's not a זבה zava here, so
if she bleeds here, she's actually a נדה. niddah. So it's true
in theory, had she been a זבה, zava, these would be related
to זבה zava days, but right now she's never going to be
a זבה zava here with the קשוי, kishuy, right? Okay, so therefore,
I mean, she could be if she has a bleeding without the
קשוי, kishuy, but she didn't, so therefore she's not going to be,
so in practice these will be נדה niddah days, not זבה zava
days. That's what לוי Levi says. Okay, so the only issue here
is, so the proof is we say you can have a forty
or fifty day stretch. And the answer is, so רבא Rava says
that because if it were she to have been a זבה zava
here, these days would be related for the law that the קשוי
kishuy says the blood is not a problem. The fact that these
are theoretical זבה zava days is enough to say the blood is
okay. Okay, it's a very lenient interpretation. So although we're saying forty
or fifty days, what the גמרא Gemara is saying is we're not
saying the entire stretch could be טהור, tahor, we're saying that's where
the laws are relevant for לוי. Levi. Sometimes she'll be טהור, tahor,
sometimes not. לשנא אחרינא, Lishna achrina, another version of this, אמרי amri
they say, אמר רב לוי, Amar Rav Levi, אין הדם מטהר אלא
ימים הראויים להיות בהם זבה גדולה. Ein hadam metaher ela yamim hareuyim
lihyot bahem zava gedola. Now, it only works, and again לוי Levi
for a little more limited, it only works for the period that
she could become a זבה גדולה. zava gedola. מאי טעמא? Mai taama?
דמיה ימים רבים כתיב Dameha yamim rabim ketiv
because the way we learned that based on the fetus she's not
a זבה, zava, it's her blood, not the blood that results from
the fetus and it says ימים רבים, yamim rabim, many days, from
which we learn three days bleeding. So what does this mean? That
what days is he excluding? So תוספות Tosafot has two versions. תוספות
Tosafot says, and then I'll tell you רש"י Rashi says. תוספות Tosafot
says it might mean even within this eleven day period, it's not
going to work for the entire eleven days because on day one
and two she can't yet be a זבה גדולה. zava gedola. So
this only works on days that could turn her into a זבה
גדולה, zava gedola, so only from day three on, because day one
and two can't be. That's one version of תוספות. Tosafot. The other
version is, no, it's day ten and eleven can't be, because you
can't start the process of a זבה גדולה zava gedola by ten
and eleven, right? Because a זבה גדולה zava gedola needs three days,
so the last time you could start the process would be nine,
ten, and eleven. But anyway, either way תוספות Tosafot is reading that
he's even more strict than before. It doesn't even work for this
entire period, only for a period that within it she could become
a זבה גדולה, zava gedola, either only starting on day three or
only ending before day ten. That's the way תוספות Tosafot reads it.
רש"י Rashi reads it in a slightly different way. He says that
it only stops her from being a זבה גדולה, zava gedola, it
doesn't stop her from being a זבה קטנה. zava ketana. So if
she bleeds with the קשוי, kishuy, whatever she bleeds, even if she
bleeds in the middle here once or twice, she's a זבה קטנה
zava ketana and she still requires one clean day. והלכה V'halacha that
קשוי kishuy is מטהר metaher her only means that she'll never become
a זבה גדולה, zava gedola, but it doesn't mean she won't become
a זבה קטנה. zava ketana. That's the way רש"י Rashi reads it.
Is that clear? So it's not so much the period of time
that it solves, but it's that it only stops her from being
a זבה גדולה, zava gedola, it doesn't stop her from being a
זבה קטנה, zava ketana, so if she bleeds with קשוי kishuy one
or two days, she's still a זבה קטנה. zava ketana. That's the
way רש"י Rashi reads it. But we'll go with תוספות Tosafot because
it's more fitting in the discussion that he's saying not the entire
eleven days, only some of them. Okay, that's this version of לוי.
Levi.
Whatever. אבא שאול משמיה דרבא אמר. Abba Shaul mishmeih d'Rava amar. Now,
אבא שאול Abba Shaul says in the name of רבא, Rava, אפילו
ימים הראויים להיות בהם זבה קטנה. Afilu yamim hareuyim lihyot bahem zava
ketana. No, it even includes the days she could become a זבה
קטנה. zava ketana. Let's say the entire eleven days. מאי טעמא? Mai
taama? ימי וכל ימי התם כתיב Yemei v'chol yemei hatam ketiv that
the same place we learned that there's a status of a זבה
קטנה, zava ketana, the תורה Torah never says זבה קטנה. zava ketana.
The תורה Torah says if a woman bleeds after her period, she
has to wait seven clean days, what we call a זבה גדולה.
zava gedola. The rabbis make a דרשה drasha that if there's the
days and all the days, that even if she only bleeds for
one or two days, she's a זבה zava for a day. She
needs one clean day afterwards. She's a זבה קטנה zava ketana for
a day. That's what the rabbis say. So he says, look, we
make that דרשה drasha in this פסוק pasuk of דמיה ימים רבים.
dameha yamim rabim. So this פסוק pasuk includes זבה קטנה. zava ketana.
So therefore it's not limited, it's the entire eleven days, not only
from day three on and so on. It's the entire eleven days.
So according to this, both approaches limit it to the eleven days.
You have no huge קולא kula going all the way out. So
let's take a look.
תנן. Tnan. So let's see how this fits in our משנה. mishna.
תנן. Tnan. כמה היא קשוייה? Kama hi kishuyah? How long does this
period last? רבי מאיר אומר אפילו ארבעים וחמישים יום. Rabbi Meir omer
afilu arbaim v'chamishim yom. Going back forty or fifty days. קשיא לתרבייהו.
Kashya l'tarveihu. This is difficult according to both of them because this
sounds like for an entire forty or fifty days she could become
טהורה. tehorah. And according to both of you, it's like it's either
nine days or eleven days. It's only days within this immediate eleven
day period.
So the גמרא Gemara says, where are we? No. מי קתני טהורה
בכולהו? Mi katani tehorah b'kulhu? We didn't say that the entire forty
or fifty days would be, she'd be טהורה. tehorah. קשתה בימי נדה
נדה בימי זיבותה טהורה. Kashta b'yemei niddah niddah, b'yemei zivutah tehorah.
It means during that forty or fifty days that is the relevant,
that is the period where the laws are applicable. But what are
the laws? The laws are that if it's during the נדה niddah
period it's still טמאה, temeiah, if it's during the זבה zava period
it's טהורה. tehorah. So yes, it only works for the eleven days
of the זבה zava period. But it works anytime within the forty
or fifty days that you will get a זבה zava period. And
you could get it more. more than once, right? She could bleed
here on January 1, and then this is a זבה Zavah period.
If it happens here, she's טהור. tahor. Then she goes another, I
don't know, twenty days, if it happened there she'd be טמא. tamei.
And but let's say it did happen there, she was טמא tamei
and she was a נדה. Niddah. And then it happened again out
here, then she would be, then it would be a זבה Zavah
again if it would be within the eleven days after a day,
day whatever, day 8 to 18. So anytime you get a זבה
Zavah period during that forty or fifty days, it works. Anytime you're
in a נדה Niddah period, it doesn't work.
Does that extend to 25 or not?
No, no, no, according to this version they're both limiting it just
to 18. Okay, but the fact that we say 40-50 days, does
that mean you're טהור tahor the entire period? It means whenever you
get a זבה Zavah section of those 40 or 50 days, then
you're טהור. tahor. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on, תניא,
Tanya, we turn the ברייתא. Baraita. היה רבי מאיר אומר, Hayo Rabbi
Meir Omer, now we're going to have a little fun math. יש
מקשה קנ יום, Yesh maksha kof nun yom, I can get a
woman that has childbirth pains and bleeding for 150 days
straight, ואין זבה עולה בהן, ve'ein Zavah oleh bahen, she'll never be
a זבה. Zavah. Okay, so what is this? How could a woman
bleed 150 days straight and never be a זבה? Zavah? כיצד. Keitzad.
שניים בלא עת, Shnayim belo et, ושבעה נדה, veshiva Niddah, ושניים שלאחר
נדה. veshnayim she'achar Niddah. Okay, let's say she first bled she was
a נדה. Niddah. And now she's in her she's pregnant, she was
a נדה Niddah somewhere in the middle of the pregnancy, she bled.
And now she's in this period between day 8 and 18. And
she bleeds these two times here, days 10 and 11. Now she's
not a זבה Zavah because she only bled two days, I mean
she's not a זבה גדולה, Zavah Gedolah, that's what we're talking about.
Then she bled nine days afterwards, seven days afterwards, she's a נדה,
Niddah, not a זבה, Zavah, she's in this area. Then the נדה
Niddah period ends, she bleeds two more days in the זבה Zavah
period, right? So she's also not a זבה, Zavah, it's only two,
she needs three. So we have 2, 7, and 2, we're up
to 11 days of bleeding and she's not yet a זבה גדולה.
Zavah Gedolah. Now you would say, okay, next day boom she's going
to be a זבה Zavah because you're in the זבה Zavah period
and you bled day 1 and 2. But let's take a look.
So you're up to 11. Now וחמישים שולד מטהר. vechamishim shevelad metaher.
This is how we know that his 50 is precise because he's
giving an exact count. Now though on day 3 is when the
50 days before childbirth begins. Okay, we're going to, I mean we
can only figure out retroactively when we see when she gave birth.
But okay. So now she's bled 2, 7, 2, she's not yet
a זבה, Zavah, but one more bleeding will make her a זבה,
Zavah, but now starts the 50 days and it comes with childbirth
pains. And so for the next 50 days of bleeding, even if
there's straight bleeding 50 days, if it's with childbirth pains, it's going
to be nothing, it's not going to make her a זבה. Zavah.
Okay, so now you have 2, 7, 2, 9, 11, and 50,
61. Okay, by the way, I should mention that this makes it
clear like the version we said before that the 50 day period
she could be טהור tahor the entire period, that you consider the
זבה Zavah period to go in, you know, once it begins it
continues indefinitely. Okay, because he says the whole 50 days even with
bleeding it's considered it's טהור. tahor. So this is clearly the idea
that the period continues indefinitely.
Even if she says to her husband wait, wait. Yes, correct. And
and she's in labor?
Well then she's in labor, it's 50 days before pregnancy.
Well she has labor pains.
Oh she has pains, yeah, she's bleeding and she's... Right. And then
and he...
And she can have sex.
Yeah, I mean nobody is saying that this is you're, okay, but
I mean maybe she's the one that wants to be having sex.
Nobody is saying that she's in the middle of childbirth,
lots of women have pains during their you know during their last
trimester, right? Cramps and pains.
Not labor, not labor.
Right, but I don't see this as being something about the man
at all, we're just trying like maybe it's for טומאה Tumah and
טהרה Taharah purposes, you know however the couple wants to act on
it, this is the הלכה Halakha that she's טהורה. Tehorah. Nobody's saying
like her husband is chomping at the bit and we have to
find a way to make her טהורה. Tehorah. It's a question, she's
טהורה, Tehorah, however they want to act on it they'll choose to
act on it.
I mean it's sort of a trivia game. Well that's also true,
it's like how many can you be over at once?
Exactly, that's also true, it's like you know the גמרא Gemara likes
doing a lot of math in הלכות נדה. Hilchos Niddah. Okay, so
anyway, but the first certainly one of the things we see here
is like the opinion of of רב אדא בר אבא Rav Ada
Bar Abba that you can be טהור tahor the entire 50 days.
Once you're in the זבה Zavah period it continues indefinitely. Okay, so
we have 11 plus 50, 61. וחמישים שולד מטהר, vechamishim shevelad metaher,
and then she gives birth, מזל טוב, Mazal Tov, and it's a
baby girl. Because the baby girl she's got another 80 days. Now
it is true she's טמאה tmeiah for two weeks, but that טומאה
Tumah is טומאת יולדת, Tumas Yoledes, and it's not טומאת זבה. Tumas
Zavah. Why is it not טומאת זבה? Tumas Zavah? Because any bleeding
she's doing that time anyway is going to first of all it's
not טומאת זבה Tumas Zavah because it's after the way after she
bled before, it's not really in her זבה Zavah period anymore, now
it's in her נדה Niddah period. But also some immediate bleeding she'll
do during that time will also be מחמת הולד machmas havalad and
so on. So now she's given birth so the blood that she
has during childbirth will not make her a זבה, Zavah, she's טומאת
יולדת, Tumas Yoledes, and then for two weeks, and then for the
next 66 days even if she bleeds she's טהורה. Tehorah. So
she had eleven, fifty, sixty-one, eighty, is one hundred and forty-one. Okay,
that's where she's up to, one hundred and forty-one. The שבע נידה,
sheva nidda, now afterwards she's continuing to bleed, so she bleeds now
for—but what is she? She's a נידה, nidda, right, because it's been
much more than day eighteen since the onset of the bleeding a
while ago. So therefore she's a נידה. nidda. So therefore for seven
days, ושנים שלאחר נידה, ushnayim she'achar nidda, and then two more days
in the זבה zava period, but you're not yet a זבה, zava,
you need to bleed three days in the זבה zava period. So
you got yet eleven, two, seven, two
before נידה נידה, nidda nidda, then two of זבה, zava, eleven, then
fifty and eighty, right, so that's one hundred and thirty plus eleven,
one hundred and forty-one plus two and seven and two again, seven
days of a נידה, nidda, two of a זבה, zava, and you're
not yet a זבה גדולה, zava gedola, that's one hundred and fifty.
All right, that's how he could get it. I think Dov is
completely right. It's just basically having fun, nobody imagines a woman to
be bleeding one hundred and
fifty days straight.
What?
Exactly.
Right. So the גמרא Gemara says אמרו לו, amru lo, they said
to רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, אם כן יש מכה שכל ימיה מזיבה
עליה בהם, im kein yesh maca shekol yameha meziva aleha bahem, a
woman could bleed every day of her life and not be a
זבה. zava. Why? Because—and it
doesn't mean—I'm sorry, but קושי koshi means bleeding with birth pains, right,
קושי, koshi, exactly, bleeding with birth pains every day of her life
and not be a זבה. zava. Why? Because you have a woman
that bled with, let's say, the fifty days of birth pains, she's
not a זבה, zava, and then she gave birth, she's eighty days
of afterwards, she's not a זבה zava because of the eighty days
of a female. Let's say during those eighty days she got pregnant
again and then miscarried at the end of eighty days. So then
you would start another eighty days or forty days again. So you
could have a woman that's constantly giving birth, miscarrying, giving birth,
miscarrying, her entire life, וכל ימיה, vechol yameha, and would never be
a זבה. zava. Right. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אמר להם, amar lahem, he said back to them, מה דעתכו, ma
datechu, what are you thinking about? משום נפלים, mishum nefalim, because of
miscarriages?
אין קושי לנפלים. ein koshi l'nefalim. Now here's an important question which
we haven't raised, which came earlier in the גמרא, Gemara, but first
time it's being raised in this discussion. If a woman has the
childbirth pains and bleeding and then it terminates not in a live
birth but it terminates in a miscarriage, does the miscarriage say that
the pain was a result from the fetus and she's טהור, tahor,
or this הלכה halacha that the pain makes the blood non-problematic is
only when it results in a live birth? So that is the
question, whether יש קושי לנפלים או אין קושי לנפלים. yesh koshi l'nefalim
o ein koshi l'nefalim. Is childbirth pains—are they—do they relate to cases
of miscarriage? Obviously, miscarriage causes the pain, but the question is הלכתית
halachically does it change the status of the blood? And he's saying
it does not. So I'm sorry, your scenario only works in cases
of multiple, consecutive miscarriages, because if she's carrying to term obviously you're
going to go a long period where she could become a זבה,
zava, right, she's pregnant and it's more than fifty days out and
so on. So your scenario only works in miscarriages. I don't think
miscarriages are relevant, because if it was a miscarriage then it is
not the laws of קושי koshi do not apply. Okay, so that's
his response, of קושי koshi do not apply. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan,
let's come in here.
By the way, you could still get a woman that's constantly bleeding
without ever being a זבה zava without the laws of קושי, koshi,
just like I said. A woman gives birth to a girl, during
the eighty days gets pregnant again, miscarries, gets pregnant again, miscarries, you
just string along in daisy chain all those eighty days of birth.
But if you wanted to work with the laws of קושי, koshi,
that part of the reason she's טהורה tehora is because the birth
made her טהורה, tehora, because of the child pains, that does not
work in cases of miscarriage. Okay. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. יש רואה
מאה יום ואין זיבה עולה בהן. yesh ro'ah me'ah yom v'ein ziva
ola bahen.
So we can do not רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir which is one
hundred and fifty, but we can do a case of one hundred.
Let's take a look.
כיצד? keitzad? שנים בלא עת, shnayim belo eis, two times after she's—the
end of a זבה zava period.
ושבע נידה, v'sheva nidda, the seven of a נידה, nidda, she's טמאה
temeiah but she's not a זבה. zava. ושנים שלאחר נידה, ushnayim she'achar
nidda, and two after she's a זבה קטנה zava ketana but not
a זבה גדולה. zava gedola. So you're back to your eleven. ושמונים
של נקבה. ushmonim shel neikeiva. Now this is not counting fifty days
out. This is counting just the period immediately prior to childbirth. So
you have eleven, then you have the childbirth, and then you have
eighty days which even if she's bleeding, again she's טומאת יולדת tumas
yoledes for the first fourteen, but she's not a זבה, zava, it's
not זבה zava blood. So you have eleven plus eighty is ninety-one.
And then after the eighty days of the girl, ושבע נידה, v'sheva
nidda, seven more she's a נידה. nidda. ושנים שלאחר נידה, ushnayim she'achar
nidda, and two more after that during the זבה zava period. So
it's eleven, eighty, and nine is one
hundred. ושלאחר נידה. veshe'achar nidda. So that's—now the point with that is
that was without any of the laws of קושי, koshi, right, that
was without any of the laws of childbirth pain. means even forgetting
the laws of childbirth pains, I can get you a hundred days
of straight bleeding. Now as I said, you can also daisy chain
multiple miscarriages and get an infinite amount of days, but without multiple
births, with a single birth, and without the laws of childbirth pain,
of קושי, koshi, I can still get a hundred days of bleeding.
Before the childbirth you have two, seven, and two, which would be
זבה קטנה, zava ketanna, נידה, nidda, זבה קטנה, zava ketanna, still not
a זבה גדולה, zava gedola, then you get 80 days where straight
up she can't be a זבה, zava, and then you get seven
and two again, נידה nidda and זבה קטנה, zava ketanna, so you
get a hundred days without קושי koshi and with single birth that
bleeding will not make her זבה. zava. So the גמרא Gemara says,
מאי קמשמע לן? mai kamashma lan? Okay, that was very lovely, but
what's the point of all of that?
So finally נפקא, nafkai, but the point of Rabbi Meir was about
אין קושי לנפלים. ein koshi l'nefalim. What's the point about this? So
לאפוקי ממאן דאמר, l'afokei mi-man d'amar, אי אפשר לפתיחת הקבר בלא דם,
i efshar lifatichat hakever belo dam, to exclude, reject the opinion that
says it's impossible to have an opening of the literally of the
grave, but of the womb here we mean, because normally this is
set in the context of miscarriage, so it calls the act of
miscarriage the opening of the grave, here it's not necessarily miscarriage, but
that's where the phrase is taken from. It's impossible to have the
opening of the womb come without blood. קמשמע לן דאפשר לפתיחת הקבר
בלא דם, kamashma lan de efshar lifatichat hakever belo dam, you can
have the opening of the womb without blood. What does that mean?
It means in the scenario we gave, two, seven, and two, two
days of being a זבה קטנה, zava ketanna, and then she gives
birth. We said, oh, she's giving birth, that's טומאת יולדת, tumat yoledet,
it won't make her into a זבה. zava. But one minute. Before
she actually became a יולדת yoledet in the process of giving birth
as the child was coming out of the womb, why don't we
say the exiting of the womb, even before the child came out
of her body and she was a יולדת, yoledet, that caused her
to bleed? And if the exiting out of the womb, the opening
of the womb caused her to bleed, that would be the third
day of bleeding, make her a זבה zava before she had the
status of a יולדת. yoledet. So the גמרא Gemara says, ah, this
is to tell me that we don't say that, we don't say
every time the woman is in the process of giving birth, you
know, that there's necessarily going to be blood. If you see blood,
there's blood, but we don't assume it and therefore the bleeding we
don't say occurred before she became a יולדת. yoledet. Now by the
way, רש"י Rashi points out who would have cared if she would
have bled during that time? If you're bleeding during childbirth, that's a
case about bleeding with קושי, koshi, right? And bleeding with קושי koshi
with the childbirth pains doesn't make you a זבה zava anyway. So
even if you would have bled it wouldn't be an issue, but
no, we are trying, though that's true, but we are trying to
describe a scenario, however impractical and impossible it might be, that there's
no childbirth pains. We're trying to say you can have a hundred
days with no childbirth pains and be טהורה. tehora. So we have
to imagine that they invented I don't know somehow, you know, painkillers
way back and a woman there was in the middle of childbirth
with absolutely no pains. Okay, of course it's impossible, but the point
is in this imagined scenario where no childbirth pains, we would still
not be concerned that she might have bled before she became a
יולדת yoledet because we don't say that opening of the womb must
entail blood. But רש"י Rashi would say that in any real-world case,
obviously she's not going to be טמאה temeia anyway because it's going
to come with childbirth pains. So if she's in her זבה zava
period, any bleeding during the act of childbirth will not make her
זבה zava because of the laws of קושי. koshi. Okay, so that
was the end of counting to getting 150 with the childbirth pains
and a hundred without it. Now רבי יהודה אומר דיה חודשה. Rabbi
Yehuda omer daiya chodsha. Rabbi Yehuda says you don't go out 50
days, her last month is enough. So we're going to see an
interesting interpretation of what that means. Let's take a look. תניא, Tanya,
we turn in the ברייתא. Baraita. רבי יהודה אומר משום רבי טרפון,
Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Tarfon, דיה חודשה, daiya chodsha, her month
is her last month is enough, ויש בדבר להקל ולהחמיר. v'yesh badavar
l'hakal u'l'hachmir. There's ways in which this is lenient or strict. It's
obviously more strict than Rabbi Meir's 40 or 50 days, but the
idea of saying exactly the ninth month can sometimes be very lenient
and can sometimes be very strict. How? Because when he says exactly
the ninth month, we'll see what he means. So he says, כיצד?
keitzad? קשתה שנים בסוף שמיני. kashta shnayim b'sof shemini. She had two
days of bleeding at the end of her eighth month. ואחד בתחלת
תשיעי. v'echad bit-chilat tishi. And one day of bleeding at the beginning
of her ninth month. ואפילו בתחלת תשיעי ילדה, v'afilu bit-chilat tishi yaldah,
even if she gave birth way at the beginning of the ninth
month, הרי זו יולדת בזוב. harei zu yoledet bezov. She's a זבה.
zava. Why? What about the fact that she had bleeding with childbirth
pains? Because he said no, to me the question is ninth month
is what I focus on. And since the majority of the three
days of bleeding, two of them were the eighth month, then this
third day of bleeding is fundamentally attributable to the eighth month and
you don't have the laws of קושי koshi and even if the
pains continued straight up to the childbirth and childbirth came on the
next day, I don't care. Most of, two out of the three
days of the bleeding were in the eighth month, she's a זבה.
zava. That's how it's very strict. It could be that you don't
get to count that, you don't get off that one day, even
though it was right before the childbirth. That's the way it's very
strict. Now, how could it be very lenient? אבל, aval, קשתה יום
אחד בסוף שמיני ושנים בתחלת תשיעי. kashta yom echad b'sof shemini v'shnayim
bit-chilat tishi. Let's say it's the reverse, one day of bleeding in
day eight and two days of bleeding in day nine. Obviously the
same would be true of all three days. Let's say it's reversed.
One day of bleeding in day eight and two days of bleeding
in day nine. Obviously the same would be true of all three
days of bleeding in day nine, but this is just parallel. If
the majority or the entirety of the three days of the bleeding
that would make her a זבה zavah come in the ninth month,
I said דם dam at ninth month, ואפילו בסוף כי ילדה. ve'afilu
besof ki yalada. Now here's the חידוש. chiddush. Even if until now
we've been saying if she bled three times at the beginning of
the ninth month, we would assume that only solves the problem of
her being a זבה zavah if she had childbirth pains leading all
the way up to the childbirth if it were at the end
of the ninth month, right we said it had to be continuous.
There couldn't be a break. But he says I'm not about continuous
and leading up. I'm about ninth month or eighth month. Any bleeding
during the ninth month with pain, not a problem. Even if there's
no continuous pain. If it's in the ninth month, it's about the
childbirth and I don't need it to lead up to the actual
act of childbirth. So that's the way it's definitely a leniency over
everything we've seen before. So he says, so it says, אבל קשתה
יום אחד בסוף שמיני ושתיים בתחילת תשיעי ואפילו בסוף כי ילדה, aval
kashda yom echad besof shemini ushtayim betchilas tish'i ve'afilu besof ki yalada,
even if it's the end of the ninth, אין זו יולדת בזוב,
ein zu yoledes bezov, it is not a יולדת בזוב yoledes bezov
even if, I mean it's not explicit here, but רש"י Rashi says
and it seems implicit, even if there was no childbirth pains leading
up till the end. To me, if it's in the ninth month
with pain you're off the hook regardless of the fact of continuous
pain or not, that doesn't bother me. Okay, so he only gives
you a month, not רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir forty-fifty days, but once
it's in that month you're totally off. You don't need any other
requirement. Okay, as long as it's again with the pains. So now
the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, amar Rav Adda bar Ahava, שמע מינה
shema mina קסבר רבי יהודה kasavar Rabbi Yehuda שיפורא גרין, shipura garin,
that the שופר shofar is the cause. What does that mean? So
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot says that it means the שופר shofar
of the announcing of the month as ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Now
who ever said we are talking about an announcing the month of
ראש חודש? Rosh Chodesh? We've been assuming we're talking about the ninth
month of her pregnancy. But תוספות Tosafot goes at great lengths to
say that somehow because he uses the language "her month" is the
cause and somehow it's an identifiable month although you'd say on the
opposite "her month" means her ninth month, but somehow the גמרא Gemara
is inferring from רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that we mean a calendar
month. Actually, it's too bad Rachel isn't here because she would like
to have heard this. Really what תוספות Tosafot proves is, is actually
no here's the point. The point is, since he's making a distinction
between two days in the ninth month and one day in the
eighth versus two days in the eighth and one day in the
ninth, how the heck do you know? How do you know when
is exactly the beginning of the ninth month? Even if you know
when the last time they had sex was, if it could have
taken up to three days for her to be pregnant, so how
do you know whether it's the exact what's the exact day of
the beginning? So therefore it says, since we can't know and he's
being so precise, he must not mean her ninth month, he must
mean the ninth calendar month. Okay, now so which basically would mean
again it's a little funny how you figure out the ninth calendar
month. Is it the day is it you take the day she
gives birth and whatever month that fell in? Or do you count
the ninth ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh since the time she became pregnant?
But whatever it is, he understands that we're talking about the ninth
calendar month. So not only is it a הלכה halacha that he
focuses on the ninth month regardless of whether the pains actually lead
all the way up to birth, if it's in the ninth month
you're off, it all of a sudden becomes a הלכה halacha that
if it's in the ninth calendar month is what it's about regardless
of whether it's in you know where it is in your exact
pregnancy. So it's about the formal calendar of בית דין. Beis Din.
Okay, so that's pretty funny that we would be so formalistic. Presumably
this has to do more with biologically what's going on with her
and that's the way why they make a point of saying שיפורא
גרין. shipura garin. It's about the הלכה halachic month, that's what determines
it even if it's you know and not her own her ninth
month per se.
It's because it's the ninth calendar month. Yeah, maybe psychologically that's a
nice way of explaining it, you know you could also say that
the גמרא Gemara thinks that there's some metaphysical implications of it being
a new ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Or it could just be that
it's not so much a biological question, it's a formal הלכה halacha
question, when do we attribute when do we say this is related
to the childbirth and you know in a formalist way we say
the ninth month of the pregnancy. It's not really a biological determination.
I understand. But the question is why do we say
it's on ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh when
the שופר shofar is blown. I understand. But we weren't saying it's
limited to ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. It's any time during that ninth
month, but the ninth month as determined by the calendar not by
her personal ninth month. That's what we're saying. Doesn't mean only on
ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. It's a way of saying the ninth calendrical
month, not her ninth personal month.
I know.
Right. Okay, but okay, let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, שיפורא גרין. shipura garin.
איני eini is this true? ואמר שמואל ve'amar Shmuel now we're going
to get into a little biology you'll find this interesting, ואמר שמואל
אין אשה מתעברת ויולדת אלא למאתים ושבעים ואחד יום, ve'amar Shmuel ein
isha misaberes veyoledes ela lamasayim veshivim ve'echad yom, 271 days. meaning
she'll be pregnant if you count the day of conception as day
one, the pregnancy will go up to day 270 and the birth
will be on day 271, in exact nine months. By the way,
is that what do we say? What is the exact term of
pregnancy? Something like that.
Is it exactly 280?
I know, but they count the 40 weeks from the last cycle,
so
it's about right.
I know it's about, I'm wondering because he's being very precise. There
is no precise.
Okay.
So
he says exactly 270, so she'll give birth on day 271, but
there is variation, but not based on women, based on how long
it took for the semen to fertilize the egg. או למאתים ושבעים
ושנים או למאתים ושבעים ושלושה O l'matayim v'shivim v'shenayim o l'matayim v'shivim
v'shlosha or 272 or 273. Why?
Because it will be exactly after 270 days of conception. So if
she conceived the night that they had sex, then it'll be on
271. If the semen did not, you know, semen can last up
to three days, so if the semen did not fertilize the egg
until the second day, it'll be on 272. If it didn't fertilize
the egg until day three, it'll be 273. So 270 days of
pregnancy, but the birth can be 71, 72, 73 based on when
the egg was fertilized. Okay, they didn't know about eggs, but you
get the point. הוא דאמר, Hu d'amar, so the גמרא, Gemara, so
how could שמואל Shmuel say that? If רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
saying that it could occur beginning of the ninth month, end of
the ninth month, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda thinks that there's a lot
of variation, שמואל, Shmuel, how do you get off saying it's so
precise, it's exactly nine full months? הוא דאמר כחסידים הראשונים. Hu d'amar
k'chasidim harishonim. He says like the early חסידים. chasidim. דתניא, Detanya, חסידים
הראשונים, chasidim harishonim, they were the early pious people. They were so
pious that לא היו משמשים מטותיהם אלא ברביעי בשבת. lo hayu meshamshim
mitoteihem ela b'revi'i b'Shabbat. They would only have sex on Wednesday שלא
יבאו נשותיהם לידי חילול שבת, shelo yavo nesholeihem lidei chillul Shabbat, they
shouldn't have
to, their wives shouldn't have to deal with, maybe they shouldn't have
to deal with the fact that their wives were giving birth on
שבת Shabbat and get into שבת Shabbat issues. Okay, so whether that's
exactly good behavior or not a good behavior, I mean obviously שבת
Shabbat is overridden for פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh and when there is
a פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh we don't hesitate at all, but they
somehow felt that it was best to avoid having to deal with
those situations. So they figured that you could be very precise in
terms of based on when you have sex, when the birth will
be. So don't have sex on Wednesday, you won't have birth on
שבת. Shabbat. So the question is: how does it work? Just Wednesday
and שבת? Shabbat? There should be more days. What's the גמרא Gemara
going to ask? Yes.
How they reconcile the idea of the three days with the אשה
מזרעת תחילה, isha mazra'at techila, מזרעת תחילה? mazra'at techila?
Doesn't the גמרא Gemara imply that there's something going on right at
the time?
No, I mean it could be that based on the current chemistry
in the body at that time. I actually had a doctor that
once told me that the אשה מזרעת תחילה isha mazra'at techila actually
had some medical truth, that the, that it changed the whatever it
was, the acidity or somehow, you know, within, you know, of the
environment and it killed off like weaker sperm and that the weaker
sperm tended to carry, you know, more one of the chromosomes rather
than the other. Somebody tried to explain it to me. Anyway, so
it doesn't mean it happens right away, it might just change the
environment and affects what's going to happen. Anyway, so they would have
sex on Wednesday, so it would not lead to giving birth on
שבת. Shabbat. Now how did that work? So the גמרא Gemara is
going to say,
ברביעי ותו לא, b'revi'i v'tu lo, just Wednesday? I mean as we
just said that there's a range of days that a woman could
give birth: 271,
72, 73. אלא אימא מרביעי ואילך, Ela eima m'revi'i v'eilach, from Wednesday
on. So how does this work? So it's very easy. How many
weeks, take out all the whole weeks from 270. So I'll make
it easy.
280 is whole weeks, right? 40 times seven is 28. So 273
is a whole week. Okay. So if she gives birth, so if
they were to have sex Friday night, right? Then it was 273
days, she'd give birth on שבת. Shabbat. If they were to have
sex on Thursday night, wait, let me do this right? No, I'm
sorry, start over. If she was to have sex on,
right,
no, Wednesday, Thursday, Friday, right, okay, let's try the days she wouldn't
have sex. She wouldn't have sex, if you had sex on Sunday,
right, if you had sex on Sunday, so 273 is, is, is,
is, you know, complete weeks, so it's שבת. Shabbat. I mean no,
seven gets you to the previous day, right? Right, if you had
seven days it would get you to שבת. Shabbat. 273 is divisible
by seven. So if she had sex on Sunday, she would give
birth on שבת. Shabbat. That's not good, so we're not going to
have sex on Sunday. If you have sex on Monday, well if
it's not 273 but 272, you'll also have sex on שבת. Shabbat.
No sex on Monday. If you have, if you have, if you
have sex on Tuesday and it's 270, not 272 but 271, it'll
also get you to שבת. Shabbat. So Sunday, Monday, or Tuesday could
get you to שבת. Shabbat. They wouldn't have sex. Wednesday, Thursday, Friday,
and שבת Shabbat will never lead to a שבת Shabbat birth. Okay,
so that's how come they did not have
sex. Where did they
get this idea from the פסוק *pasuk*? דכתיב *Dechtiv* ויתן ה' לה
הריון *Vayiten Hashem lah herayon*.
God gave her, this is right by רות *Ruth*, a pregnancy. הריון
*Herayon*, pregnancy, בגימטריא *be'gematria* מאתיים ושבעים ואחד הוה *masayim v'shivim v'echad hava*
is 271. The word הריון *herayon*. And the 272, 273 is really
based on 271. It's 271 from conception, which leads to 272, 273
from sex. But the word הריון *herayon* is 271. אמר מר זוטרא
*Amar Mar Zutra*, אפילו למאן דאמר יולדת לתשעה אינה יולדת למקוטעין *afilu
leman d'amar yoledes l'tisha aina yoledes l'mekutain*. Even according to the approach
of שמואל *Shmuel* that if a woman gives birth in her ninth
month, she does not give birth in the middle of the month,
it's only after a full nine months. That's the approach of שמואל
*Shmuel*. יולדת לשבע יולדת למקוטעין *Yoledes l'sheva yoledes l'mekutain*. If she gives
birth in the seventh month, this is the irony, that the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* understands that an eighth-month-old baby will not survive if it's
born in the eighth month, but in the seventh month it will
survive. And now we're saying even if you say a ninth-month baby
will always be carried to term and will always be a full
nine months, but maybe one in the seventh month could be even
viable and born at the beginning of the seventh month. יולדת לשבע
יולדת למקוטעין *Yoledes l'sheva yoledes l'mekutain* can even be born at the
beginning, meaning a half month, a partial month at the beginning of
the seventh month. שנאמר *She'ne'emar*, the verse says, ויהי לתקופת הימים ותהר
חנה ותלד בן *vayehi litkufas hayamim vatahar Chana vataled ben*. It was
after the period of days and חנה
*Chana* became pregnant and she gave birth to a child. מיעוט תקופות
שתים *Miut tkufos shtayim*. So תקופה *tkufa* is a period, a season.
So a season is three months. So תקופות *tkufos* are two seasons,
six months. מיעוט ימים שנים *Miut yamim shnayim* and days are two.
So six months and two days gets you just into the seventh
month. And it's reading it therefore very literally and saying she was
just into her seventh month and she gave birth. So you see
if it's the seventh month it could be at the beginning. Okay,
but anyway what you did see was the interesting debate about whether
a woman's, whether we assume like שמואל *Shmuel* that it's full nine
months and exactly precise, and the interesting point that anytime there is,
according to רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*, bleeding with pains in the ninth
month, regardless of whether the pain leads up to it, she is
not a, she, it's not a problem if it's זבה zava. *zava*
blood and the idea of the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* that that was
based on a calendar month. Now we have the last opinion of
רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* that just give
her two weeks. Let's take a look. רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים
אין קושי koshi יותר משתי שבתות *Rabbi Yosi v'Rabbi Shimon omrim ein
koshi yoser mi'shtei shabbosos*. No more than two weeks. אמר שמואל *Amar
Shmuel*, מאי טעמייהו דרבנן *mai tammaihu d'rabbanan*? What's the reasoning of the
רבנן *rabbanan*, meaning רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*,
that say only two weeks does this law apply? דכתיב וטמאה שבועיים
כנדתה *Dechtiv v'tamei shvuayim k'nidasah*. One of the places we learn out
that bleeding during the זבה zava *zava* based on the pregnancy does
not make her a זבה zava, *zava* is from the verse by
the יולדת *yoledes*, and it says she'll be טמאה *tmeiah* two weeks
like her נדה nida, *niddah*. כנדתה ולא כזיבתה *K'nidasah v'lo k'zivasah*. Meaning
only like נדה nida *niddah* is relevant during this time of childbirth,
but not זבה zava. *zava*. And from there we learn out that
if a woman is זבה zava, *zava* blood based on the fetus,
it's not a problem. מכלל דזיבתה טהורה *Miklal d'zivasah tehorah*. So זבה
zava. *zava* blood is טהורה *tehorah* if it's based on the fetus.
דכמה *De'kama*? How much? Well the פסוק *pasuk* says two weeks. וטמאה
שבועיים *V'tamei shvuayim*. Which means if it's זבה zava. *zava*, it's not.
For two weeks she's not טמאה *tmeiah*. שבועיים *Shvuayim*. So two weeks.
So we get it from the פסוק *pasuk*. The פסוק *pasuk* mentions
two weeks. From there we learn out that זבה zava, *zava* is
טהורה *tehorah*. So we say the same amount of time, two weeks.
תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan: *Tanu Rabbanan*. So now we have a ברייתא
Baraita, *beraita*. יש מקשה עשרים וחמישה יום ואין זיבה ziva עולה בהן
*Yesh maksha esrim v'chamisha yom v'ein ziva ola bahen*. So before we
had a hundred days, a hundred and fifty days, now we're being
much more modest. Now we're saying twenty-five days of bleeding with pain.
כיצד *Keitzad*? How do you get it? שניים בלא עת ושבעה נדה
nida ובשניים שלאחר נדה nida *shnayim belo eis v'shiva
niddah u'v'shnayim she'le'achar niddah*. Back to your eleven. And now they only
have fourteen days that the bleeding with קושי koshi *koshi* is not
a problem. וארבעה עשר יום שהולד מטהר *v'arba'ah asar yom she'havlad mitaher*.
Plus the fourteen days. Okay. ואי אפשר שתתקשה עשרים ושישה יום בלא
ולד belo valad. ולא תהא יולדת בזובה *V'ee efshar she'titkashe esrim v'shisha
yom belo vlad v'lo tehei yoledes be'zova*. And she cannot have a
bleeding of 26 days. It's only 25. Anything more בלא ולד *belo
vlad* is without a child and ולא תהא יולדת בזובה *v'lo tehei
yoledes be'zova* and it will not be a problem of being a
זבה zava. *zava*. You can get up to 25 days bleeding. Now
by the way, before we gave huge numbers, 100, 150, that's because
we were including the period after childbirth. They're just, the reason their
number is so much smaller is they're talking just about the period
before childbirth. So they are saying that you cannot get, that you
can only get up to 25 days of bleeding before childbirth without
being a זבה zava. *zava*. 2, 7 and 2 is 11. 14
days where the laws of קושי Koshi *koshi* apply. 25. 25 days
of bleeding without being a זבה zava *zava* before childbirth. If it
were 26, you would have to be a זבה zava, *zava*. Because
then it would be three days of bleeding during the זבה Zava.
*zava* period and 26 you'd have to be a זבה Zava. *zava*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says the only funny part about that
was it says you can't have 26 days of bleeding without a
child. What do you mean without a child? You are giving birth.
So probably what it means is 26 days of bleeding before childbirth.
But that wasn't what they said. So the גמרא *Gemara* says בלא
ולד *belo vlad*? If there's no... child, ובתלתא נמי סגי, even three
days of bleeding will make you a זבה. Zava The only reason
she’s not a זבה Zava is because it’s leading up to childbirth.
What do you mean without a child? So again, the simple explanation
of this is if you have 25 days of bleeding up till
childbirth without having given birth yet and not be a זבה, Zava.
but 26 you’ll already be a זבה. Zava. But it didn’t say
without having given birth, it said בלא ולד. So how do you
read this? בלא ולד בתלתא נמי סגי. Belo valad betlata nami sagi.
אמר רב ששת Amar Rav Sheshet אימא במקום
שיש
ולד. eima bimkom sheyesh valad. Switch the text! It doesn’t mean without
a child, it means when you have a child. Okay. אמר ליה
רבא, Amar lei Rava, רבא Rava said והא בלא ולד תניא, veha
belo valad tanya, you can’t do that. It says without a child!
אלא אמר רבא Ella amar Rava הכי קאמר, hachi ka’amar, this is
what it means: אי אפשר שתתקשה עשרים וששה יום במקום שיש ולד
ולא תהא יולדת בזוב. i efshar shetitkasheh esrim veshisha yom bimkom sheyesh
valad velo tehei yoledes bezov.
You can’t have 26 days of bleeding prior to childbirth if there’s
a child without being a זבה, Zava, it can only be up
to 25 before. Once it’s 26, you’ll definitely be a זבה. Zava.
ובמקום שאין ולד, Ubimkom she’ein valad, and if there’s no child, אלא
נפל, ella nefel, meaning no live birth, but it’s going to be
a miscarriage, בתלתא נמי הויא זבה. betlata nami havya zava. Then even
with three days, it does, you’re a זבה. Zava, You don’t get
any days to be okay. Why? מאי טעמא? Mai ta’ama? אין קושי
לנפלים. ein koshi linefalim. Like we said before, all these laws of
קושי Koshi of the childbirth pains making it not דם זיבה dam
zivah only apply when it’s a live birth. If it is a
miscarriage, then any period before, if there was bleeding during זבה, Zava
even with pains, you are going to be a זבה. Zava, Okay,
so was once again figuring out how many days you can do,
rather than getting huge numbers of 100, 150 when you include the
period after childbirth. This was focusing on the period before and got
you up to 25 days. More than that, she would have to
be a זבה. Zava? Okay, so that was end of that discussion
about
when does the קושי get you off during the זבה Zava. period
and the break. If there’s a break then you can’t connect this
with the childbirth. And how much before? 40 days, 50 days, a
month, a week, two weeks and so on. Let’s take a look
now at the next משנה, Mishnah, a fascinating debate
about what happens about bleeding during the טהרה tohora period after childbirth.
So: המקשה בתוך שמונים של נקבה קודם שיצא ולד. Hamaksheh betoch shemonim
shel nekeivah kodem sheyeitzei valad. Let’s say a woman is during her
80 days, and focus on the טהור tahor days, the 66 טהור
tahor days of after birth of a girl. And she is having
childbirth pain. Now how is she having childbirth pain? She just gave
birth. So it could be she got pregnant again, or it could
be of course that really or it could be, רש"י Rashi imagines
a case where there was twins, one child came out and the
other did not yet come out and you know we have so
that has happened in the past. We actually heard world Guinness Book
of World Records, I don’t know, 60 days or whatever. So she
gave birth here to a girl and now during the next 66
days either she’s pregnant again or there’s still a baby that hasn’t
come out and she’s bleeding with childbirth pains. Now what would you
imagine? You would imagine look, during these 66 days of טהרה, toharah,
even if there were no childbirth pains her bleeding she’d be טהור.
tahor. So how much more so if it came with childbirth pains
that she should be טהור tahor during this period, right? This is
a טהור tahor period. So let’s see what the משנה Mishnah says.
The משנה Mishnah says it’s not a problem, any blood during this
period not a problem. That’s what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says
until the birth. רבי אליעזר מטמא. Rabbi Eliezer metamei. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says no, it is a problem. This blood during this טהור
tahor period based on the fetus. How could that be a problem?
אמרו לו לרבי אליעזר, Amru lo leRabbi Eliezer, they said to רבי
אליעזר: Rabbi Eliezer: ומה במקום שהחמיר בדם השופע הקל בדם הקושי, u'mah
bimkom shehechmir bedam hashofei hekel bedam hakoshi, when it was before childbirth
that if she bled without pains she’d be a זבה, zava, we’re
strict about normal bleeding, we’re going to be lenient about bleeding with
pains.
מקום שהקל בדם השופע, Makom shehekel bedam hashofei, during these 66 days
that normal bleeding is anyway טהור, tahor, אינו
דין שנקל בדם הקושי? eino din shenakel bedam hakoshi? How much more
so should we be lenient if it is bleeding with pains? Right,
it’s crazy. Here the normal bleeding is טהור, tahor, so how much
more so should the bleeding with pains be טהור. tahor. Now that
is such an obvious point, what is going into רבי אליעזר's Rabbi
Eliezer’s head? So רש"י Rashi tells us and the גמרא will tell
us, actually here’s what he’s thinking. He said the תורה Torah says
she’s טהור tahor here because it’s saying that this is blood that
resulted from the childbirth. That’s why this blood is טהור. tahor. But
if this blood is not resulting from the previous childbirth but resulting
from the current fetus in her, then it doesn’t get the pass.
It doesn’t get treated as a דם טהור dam tahor because it’s
coming from a different cause. So the fact that you can attribute
it to a different cause here makes it worse, not better, because
the only reason this is טהור tahor is because it’s attributed to
the previous birth. Okay, that’s his implicit logic. But they’re saying look,
this is a טהור tahor period, how can you say this? So
אמר להם, Amar lahem, what did he say back? אמר להם, Amar
lahem, he said back to them: דיו לבא מן הדין להיות כנדון.
Dayo lova min hadin lihyot kenidon. No,
if you make a קל וחומר kal vachomer you can’t exceed what
you’re making the קל וחומר kal vachomer based on. ממה הקל עליה
מטומאת זיבה אבל טמאה טומאת נדה. mimah hekel aleiha mitumat zivah aval
tmeiah tumat niddah.
When the דם קושי dam koshi gets you off. off the hook.
What does דם קושי Dam Koshi get you off the hook from?
From being a זבה. zava But even with דם קושי, Dam Koshi,
if it's during the נידה Nidda period, you're a נידה. Nidda. So
he's saying, look, I will admit the laws of דם קושי Dam
Koshi apply during these 66 days. What are the laws of דם
קושי? Dam Koshi? You're not a זבה. zava. Fine, but if it's
during her נידה Nidda period, she'll still be a נידה. Nidda. So
basically what he is saying is, I'm just going to give it
normal laws of דם קושי. Dam Koshi. No זבה zava. but yes
נידה. Nidda. And they're saying, but a woman who bleeds during this
period is not a זבה zava, or a נידה, Nidda, she's nothing.
So why are you being more strict here than even if the
blood had come without any pain? So let's take a look at
the גמרא. תנו רבנן: we learned in the ברייתא, the same debate
with a little more clarification.
תשב: Teshev: she shall sit for 66 days, לרבות המקשה בתוך שמונים
של נקבה שכל דמים שהיא רואה טהורים עד שיצא הולד.
Lerabot HaMakshisha Betoch Shemonim Shel Nekevah Shekol Damim She'roah Tehorim Ad
She'yetze Havalad.
רבי אליעזר מטמא, Rabbi Eliezer Metamei, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is מטמא.
Metamei. אמרו לו לרבי אליעזר, Amru Lo L'Rabbi Eliezer, they said to
רבי אליעזר: Rabbi Eliezer: ומה במקום שהחמיר בשופי שלפני הולד
הקל בקושי שלפני הולד מקום שהקל בשופי שלאחר הולד שכל דמים שהיא
רואה טהורים אינו דין שנקל בקושי שלאחר הולד?
V'ma B'makom She'hechmir B'shofei
She'lifnei Havalad Heikel B'koshi She'lifnei Havalad Mekom She'heikel B'shofei She'achar Havalad Shekol
Damim She'roah Tehorim Eino Din She'neikel B'koshi She'achar Havalad? אמר להם, Amar
Lahem, he said to them fine, דיו לבוא מן הדין להיות כנדון.
Dayo Lavo Min HaDin Lihyot KeNidon.
But what you learn out can't be more from what you started
from. ממה הקל לנו? Mi'mah Heikel Lenu? מטומאת זיבה. Mi'tumat Ziva. Yes,
we do apply laws of pains, but what does
childbirth pains get you out of? They get you out of being
a זבה. zava So fine, during these 66 days with the pains,
she's not a זבה. אבל טמאה טומאת נידה, Aval Tammei Tumat Nidda,
but it only gets you out of זבה, she'll still be a
נידה. Nidda. So I'm not impressed by that. אמרו לו: Amru Lo:
they said to him, הרי אנו משיבים לך לשון אחר. Harei Anu
Meshivim Lach Lashon Acher. Let's try it from a different way. You
got it's a nice language, we're going to respond to you with
a different language, let's rephrase it. I want to rephrase, tell him
I'm going to rephrase it, yes I'm going to rephrase it. ומה
במקום: U'ma B'makom: so until now we're saying that the same way
we're lenient about the pain here, we should be lenient here. And
he says fine, we're going to have it the same law. The
same law is no pain, is you're not a זבה. So now
they're going to say no no, let's not compare the pain before
to the pain after. Let's compare the pain after to the non-pain
after. Non-pain after you're going to be טהור. Tahor. So pain after
you should certainly be טהור, Tahor, right? So the same way without
pains any bleeding here you're nothing, so with pain you should also
be nothing. That's a better קל וחומר. Kal VaChomer. Okay. ומה במקום
שהחמיר בשופי שלפני הולד הקל בקושי שעמו. U'ma B'makom She'hechmir B'shofei She'lifnei
Havalad Heikel B'koshi She'imo.
Before childbirth, we restrict by normal bleeding and we're lenient by bleeding
with pain. So bleeding with pain is always more lenient than bleeding
without pain, right? מקום שהקל בשופי שלאחר הולד: Mekom She'heikel B'shofei She'achar
Valad: during these 66 days, bleeding without pain is nothing,
totally טהור. Tahor. So therefore אינו דין שנקל בקושי שעמו? Eino Din
She'neikel B'koshi She'imo? How much more so should when it comes with
pain never be stricter than without pain. Do you understand the difference
of the two arguments? One argument is this pain should be no
stricter than that pain. Fine, no stricter, but you're still a נידה.
Nidda. So okay, forget that. Not no stricter than that pain. This
pain should be no stricter than the bleeding without the pain. Bleeding
with pain is always less strict than bleeding without, and bleeding without
you're טהור, Tahor, so bleeding with you should be טהור. Tahor. That's
what he says. So אמר להם: Amar Lahem: he said back to
them, אפילו אתם משיבים כל היום כולו, Afilu Atem Meshivim Kol Hayom
Kulo, you can go ahead and reframe this the entire day
long, but דיו לבוא מן הדין להיות כנדון. Dayo Lavo Min HaDin
Lihyot KeNidon. You're never going to get beyond where you started. The
whole thing hinges on the idea that קושי gets you out of
זבה, so at the end of the day you're never going to
get out of that starting point that you'll get out of זבה
but you can't prove beyond that. Okay. ממה
הקל להם? Mi'mah Heikel Lahem? מטומאת זיבה: Mi'tumat Ziva: all you can
start from is that קושי gets you out of
זבה, אבל טמאה טומאת נידה: Aval Tammei Tumat Nidda: she will still
be a נידה. Nidda. Ironically, if she has pain during these 66
days, it'll be stricter than not having pain. And now we are
finally going to see the reason for this. It seems bizarre. I
gave you the reason so you wouldn't be confounded, but now רבא
Rava is going to say the reason. And the reason makes a
lot of sense. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: בהא זכינו רבי אליעזר לרבנן.
B'ha Zakinu Rabbi Eliezer L'Rabbanan. In this way רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
could have totally beaten out the rabbis and shown them the logic
of his bizarre position. לאו אמרתם דמה? Lav Amritam Damah? How do
we know that pain beforehand as a result of childbirth does not
make you a זבה? Because the דרשה Drasha was her blood. דמה
מחמת עצמה ולא מחמת ולד. Damah Machmat Atzmah V'lo Machmat Valad. When
it's coming from herself, not as a result from the fetus. That's
how we know that pain beforehand does not make you a זבה.
So here too you should think the same דרשה Drasha in the
reverse. הכא נמי: Hacha Nami: what it says here too it says
וטהרה ממקור. V'tahara Mimkor. So here too you think the same דרשה
drasha in the reverse הכא נמי hacha nami what it says here
too it says טהרה ממקור דמיה tahara mimkor dameha during the sixty-six
days she will be pure from her wellspring of her blood ממקור
דמיה מחמת עצמה mimkor dameha machmat atzma when it's her own blood
during those sixty-six days, when it's naturally coming from her, it's טהור.
tahor. ולא מחמת ולד velo machmat vlad when it's coming as a
result of the fetus, the Torah did not give you a pass,
which makes a lot of sense. The reason you're off during these
sixty-six days is it results, it's seen as being connected to the
previous childbirth. But here where it's attributable to something else, maybe you
don't get a pass. It's true you won't be a זבה, we're
not going to make it more strict than that law, but you
should at least be a נדה, nida that's Rabbi Eliezer's argument. So
the גמרא just ends by saying אימא בימי נדה נדה בימי זיבה
טהורה. eima bimei nida nida bimei ziva tehora. So why can't the
way תוספות Tosafot reads this is, hold on let me just check
תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says one minute,
right, why couldn't the, so what would the rabbis say back? They
would say back no, you want to say that during this period
she'll be a נדה nida. during the נדה period and a זבה
during the זיבה ziva period and nothing during the זיבה period, that's
what you want to conclude, that she can become a נדה during
this period but not a זבה. So אמר קרא תשב ישיבה אחת
לכולן. amar kra teshev yeshiva achat lekulan. The rabbis say look, you
make a good argument, maybe you're trying to say she should be
able to be a נדה during this time, but you admit she
can't be a זבה. And once she can't be a זבה, she
can't be anything. The Torah says she shall sit in her pure
state, so it has to be completely consistent, and since she's going
to be טהור tahor from being a זבה during this time, she's
going to be טהור tahor from being a נדה. Okay, and that
is the end of that.